Hello, my name is David Brown and this is a pronunciation class.
مرحباً، اسمي ديفيد براون وهذا درس في النطق.
Hi, welcome. How are you?
مرحباً، أهلاً بك. كيف حالك؟
Hello, thank you. I'm doing well. And you?
مرحباً، شكراً لك. أنا بخير. وأنت؟
I'm doing great. Thank you. What's your name?
أنا بخير جداً. شكراً لك. ما اسمك؟
My name is Lourdes. Lourdes Landa.
اسمي لورديس (Lūrdis). لورديس لاندا.
Hi, Ms. Lourdes. Welcome. I'm Mr. Brown. Where are you from?
مرحباً يا آنسة لورديس. أهلاً بك. أنا الأستاذ براون. من أين أنتِ؟
I'm from Tegucigalpa Honduras.
أنا من تيغوسيغالبا، هندوراس.
Okay, Tegucigalpa. Awesome. My wife is from Tegucigalpa.
حسناً، تيغوسيغالبا. رائع. زوجتي من تيغوسيغالبا.
Oh, that's nice.
أوه، هذا لطيف.
Yeah, nice to meet you.
نعم، سررت بلقائك.
Nice to meet you, too.
وأنا أيضاً سررت بلقائك.
I see that you selected a lesson about these different TH sounds. Is that okay?
أرى أنكِ اخترتِ درساً عن أصوات TH المختلفة هذه. هل هذا مناسب؟
Yes, that's right.
نعم، هذا صحيح.
Okay, we have two sounds that can be tricky. We have the TH sound that is voiceless and the TH sound, which is voiced.
حسناً، لدينا صوتان قد يكونان مربكين. لدينا صوت TH المهموس وصوت TH الجهوري.
Both involve putting your tongue between your teeth.
كلاهما يتضمن وضع لسانك بين أسنانك.
One, the voiced one has a vibration and the voiceless one does not have a vibration.
أحدهما، الجهوري، به اهتزاز والمهموس ليس به اهتزاز.
We need to know when to use this and when to remember how to use these different sounds here.
نحتاج أن نعرف متى نستخدم هذا ومتى نتذكر كيف نستخدم هذه الأصوات المختلفة هنا.
So we'll start. So a question. Have you ever said is sync when you meant to say think or free instead of three?
إذاً سنبدأ. سؤال. هل سبق لكِ أن قلتِ "sync" عندما كنتِ تقصدين قول "think" أو "free" بدلاً من "three"؟
I think I've done that before you.
أعتقد أنني فعلت ذلك من قبل.
And it's pretty common. Even some native speakers, some native speakers, for example, will say birth day with an F instead of a TH sound.
وهذا شائع جداً. حتى بعض المتحدثين الأصليين، بعض المتحدثين الأصليين، على سبيل المثال، سيقولون "birth day" بصوت F بدلاً من صوت TH.
A little bit of practice. You know where to put your tongue. If you know what sound it makes where the sounds come from.
القليل من التدريب. تعرفين أين تضعين لسانك. إذا عرفتِ ما هو الصوت الذي يصدره ومن أين تأتي الأصوات.
It can easily be fixed. You can learn to hear and produce these differences and sounds.
يمكن إصلاحه بسهولة. يمكنكِ تعلم سماع وإنتاج هذه الاختلافات في الأصوات.
Okay.
حسناً.
So here are some objectives. I'd like for you to read these.
إذاً إليكِ بعض الأهداف. أود منكِ أن تقرئيها.
Well, I want you to listen to these objectives here. So we're going to be able to distinguish between these T8 sounds. We have the voiceless and the voiced fricatives.
حسناً، أريدكِ أن تستمعي إلى هذه الأهداف هنا. إذاً سنكون قادرين على التمييز بين أصوات TH هذه. لدينا الأصوات الاحتكاكية المهموسة والجهورية.
We're going to describe and demonstrate the correct mouth movements mechanics for these different sounds.
سنصف ونوضح حركات الفم الصحيحة وآلياتها لهذه الأصوات المختلفة.
I will be able to produce these accurately in isolated words and also in short phrases as well. So we'll try to use them in context.
سأكون قادراً على إنتاج هذه الأصوات بدقة في كلمات منفصلة وكذلك في عبارات قصيرة أيضاً. لذا سنحاول استخدامها في سياقها.
And we'll try to recognize and come and spelling patterns associated with TH.
وسنحاول التعرف على أنماط الإملاء الشائعة المرتبطة بـ TH.
And you need to basically notice and correct yourself whenever you use TH and practice.
وتحتاجين بشكل أساسي إلى ملاحظة وتصحيح نفسكِ كلما استخدمتِ TH والتدرب.
So it's some fine tuning for pronunciation in today's class.
إذاً هو بعض الضبط الدقيق للنطق في درس اليوم.
How do you feel about your pronunciation? Do you feel like you need to work on your pronunciation?
كيف تشعرين تجاه نطقكِ؟ هل تشعرين أنكِ بحاجة إلى العمل على نطقكِ؟
Yes, definitely.
نعم، بالتأكيد.
Okay. I think this is a good class even for some of us native speakers to as well. So no worries if you feel nervous. It's completely normal.
حسناً. أعتقد أن هذا درس جيد حتى لبعضنا نحن المتحدثين الأصليين أيضاً. لذا لا تقلقي إذا شعرتِ بالتوتر. هذا طبيعي تماماً.
And don't feel afraid to be silly. It's a pretty silly class when you're making weird sounds with your tongue and teeth.
ولا تخافي من أن تبدي سخيفة. إنه درس سخيف نوعاً ما عندما تصدرين أصواتاً غريبة بلسانكِ وأسنانكِ.
Thank you.
شكراً لك.
That improving this can help you in your daily conversations or at work. By the way, Lord, what do you do? What is your job?
تحسين هذا يمكن أن يساعدكِ في محادثاتكِ اليومية أو في العمل. بالمناسبة يا لورديس، ماذا تعملين؟ ما هي وظيفتكِ؟
I actually work with the government.
أنا أعمل في الواقع مع الحكومة.
The legal department in an office.
في القسم القانوني في مكتب.
And there's just a few people that can actually speak English. So when something like that comes near my help.
وهناك عدد قليل فقط من الأشخاص الذين يمكنهم التحدث باللغة الإنجليزية بالفعل. لذا عندما يحدث شيء من هذا القبيل، يحتاجون لمساعدتي.
And I think that is going to be very useful if I know the proper way to pronounce these kind of words because it gets confused.
وأعتقد أنه سيكون مفيداً جداً إذا عرفت الطريقة الصحيحة لنطق هذا النوع من الكلمات لأنه يتم الخلط بينها.
Okay, definitely. So you have a good reason to practice this today and to improve your pronunciation.
حسناً، بالتأكيد. إذاً لديكِ سبب وجيه للتدرب على هذا اليوم وتحسين نطقكِ.
We need to understand these two different sounds and what voiceless and voiced means because well, anytime we talk, we can feel vibrations or not.
نحتاج إلى فهم هذين الصوتين المختلفين وما يعنيه الصوت المهموس والصوت الجهوري، لأنه حسناً، في أي وقت نتحدث، يمكننا أن نشعر بالاهتزازات أو لا نشعر بها.
So if you put your hands in front of your throat here, if you can do that for me.
لذا إذا وضعتِ يديكِ أمام حلقكِ هنا، هل يمكنكِ فعل ذلك من أجلي.
And just start talking. Say something. Maybe a phrase.
وابدئي في التحدث فقط. قولي شيئاً ما. ربما عبارة.
Hello, my name is Noah. Hi. Yes, I can definitely feel that.
مرحباً، اسمي نوح. مرحباً. نعم، يمكنني بالتأكيد الشعور بذلك.
So you see that there are moments when it vibrates and moments when it doesn't vibrate.
إذاً ترين أن هناك لحظات يهتز فيها ولحظات لا يهتز فيها.
Essentially, these voiced sounds with ED at the end voiced are vowel sounds that will find in different parts of the word.
بشكل أساسي، هذه الأصوات الجهرية، المتعلقة بنهاية ED، هي أصوات حركات (علة) سنجدها في أجزاء مختلفة من الكلمة.
These are voiced sounds. And the ones, the sounds that we make that don't vibrate here are the voiceless ones.
هذه أصوات جهرية. والأصوات التي نصدرها ولا تهتز هنا هي الأصوات المهموسة.
So we see in the chart that we have two different examples, one for the voiceless thick.
لذا نرى في الرسم البياني أن لدينا مثالين مختلفين، أحدهما للمهموس thick.
And there's no vibration. So if you put your hand here, if you put your hand here for me and say, thick,
ولا يوجد اهتزاز. لذا إذا وضعتِ يدكِ هنا، إذا وضعتِ يدكِ هنا من أجلي وقلتِ، thick،
thick, you shouldn't, you shouldn't feel any vibration at all for that one, right?
thick، لا يجب أن تشعري بأي اهتزاز على الإطلاق لذلك الصوت، أليس كذلك؟
Again, thick, no vibration. Maybe for the, yes, but for the TH, no, right?
مرة أخرى، thick، لا اهتزاز. ربما لـ، نعم، ولكن ليس لـ TH، أليس كذلك؟
Now, this next one, please, you try again, even the tongue vibrates, right?
الآن، هذا التالي، من فضلكِ، حاولي مرة أخرى، حتى اللسان يهتز، أليس كذلك؟
So if vibrates, yeah, all the way up, this vibration and the vocal track continues onward,
لذا إذا اهتز، نعم، على طول الطريق للأعلى، يستمر هذا الاهتزاز والمسار الصوتي للأمام،
and we have this voice sound with these. So we have the voice sound with TH and with this vowel sound here.
ولدينا هذا الصوت الجهوري مع هذه. لذا لدينا الصوت الجهوري مع TH ومع صوت الحركة (العلة) هذا هنا.
So a certain consonants can also come along with different types of voice sounds too, like these voiced fricatives.
لذا يمكن أن تأتي بعض الحروف الساكنة أيضاً مع أنواع مختلفة من الأصوات الجهرية أيضاً، مثل هذه الأصوات الاحتكاكية الجهرية.
So this is the sound in words like, think with no vibration, right?
إذاً هذا هو الصوت في كلمات مثل، think بدون اهتزاز، أليس كذلك؟
Thank, then, back, path and three.
Thank, then, back, path و three.
Thank.
Thank.
Now, make sure that your tongue goes between your teeth. Can you read this part for us here?
الآن، تأكدي من أن لسانكِ يمر بين أسنانكِ. هل يمكنكِ قراءة هذا الجزء لنا هنا؟
Think, think, think, think, back, three.
Think, think, think, think, back, three.
Okay, good. So notice that these don't vibrate.
حسناً، جيد. إذاً لاحظوا أن هذه لا تهتز.
So we don't want to confuse these and say, think, for example, the sounds more like a dip sound.
لذا لا نريد الخلط بين هذه وقول، think، على سبيل المثال، الصوت يبدو أشبه بصوت dip.
We don't want to use voice fricatives when we're not supposed to and vice versa.
لا نريد استخدام الأصوات الاحتكاكية الجهرية عندما لا يفترض بنا ذلك والعكس صحيح.
So it takes some memory and some vibration here.
لذا يتطلب الأمر بعض الذاكرة وبعض الاهتزاز هنا.
So we practice the TH sound here. Remember, you should feel no buzz there.
لذا نتدرب على صوت TH هنا. تذكري، لا يجب أن تشعري بأي طنين هناك.
Let's try this again. We'll try the, and the, the, for the sound, you can feel a little bit of air on your hand.
دعنا نحاول هذا مرة أخرى. سنجرب الـ، والـ، الـ، بالنسبة للصوت، يمكنكِ الشعور ببعض الهواء على يدكِ.
Can you say,
هل يمكنكِ القول،
I guess the, uh, at the end is a bit.
أعتقد أن الـ، آه، في النهاية قليلاً.
What the, uh, I think, what the TH sound there is not voiced.
ماذا، آه، أعتقد، صوت TH هناك ليس جمهورياً.
It's a subtle difference, but an important one for pronunciation.
إنه فرق دقيق، ولكنه مهم للنطق.
So we can see some differences between these.
لذا يمكننا رؤية بعض الاختلافات بين هذه.
Essentially, they only difference.
بشكل أساسي، هما الفرق الوحيد.
You have the tongue between both, uh, tongue between your teeth and both of these pictures.
لديكِ اللسان بين كلتا، آه، اللسان بين أسنانكِ في كلتا هاتين الصورتين.
But for the voiced fricative, you also have that vibration.
ولكن بالنسبة للصوت الاحتكاكي الجهوري، لديكِ أيضاً ذلك الاهتزاز.
Alright, so I think I've explained that and you understand, right?
حسناً، إذاً أعتقد أنني شرحت ذلك وأنتِ فهمتِ، أليس كذلك؟
This is the sound in words like now we have the buzz.
هذا هو الصوت في كلمات مثل، الآن لدينا الطنين.
I think I do. I know I have to practice.
أعتقد أنني أفهم. أعرف أنني يجب أن أتدرب.
So we have the buzz sound in these words. So listen to me say it once.
إذاً لدينا صوت الطنين في هذه الكلمات. لذا استمعي إليّ أقولها مرة واحدة.
We have this. So you have a vibration.
لدينا this. إذاً لديكِ اهتزاز.
This, that, then, mother, breathe, and they, you try.
This, that, then, mother, breathe, و they, حاولي أنتِ.
Okay, let's see.
حسناً، دعنا نرى.
Breathe, that, then, mother, breath, they.
Breathe, that, then, mother, breath, they.
Good. This one here. Breathe, breathe, breathe, breathe.
جيد. هذا هنا. Breathe, breathe, breathe, breathe.
Good. Breathe.
جيد. Breathe.
Huh? So notice that vibration there should be like a sound, like a buzz.
هاه؟ إذاً لاحظوا أن الاهتزاز هناك يجب أن يكون مثل صوت، مثل طنين.
Breathe. Good.
Breathe. جيد.
Much better.
أفضل بكثير.
I think you see fear to make the other sound.
أعتقد أنكِ ترين الخوف من إصدار الصوت الآخر.
Another example of some sounds that have a voiced one will be like the letter S.
مثال آخر لبعض الأصوات التي لها صوت جهوري سيكون مثل حرف S.
Sometimes it makes a sound too, versus that sound, which is voiceless.
أحياناً يصدر صوتاً أيضاً، مقابل ذلك الصوت المهموس.
So the only difference there.
إذاً هذا هو الفرق الوحيد هناك.